welcome to meditating with john vervicky
this is an unusual setup
uh but we're trying to deal with uh
transitional times
uh we live stream every weekday morning
at 9 30 a.m
that's eastern time mondays we alternate
between a dharma day in which i teach a
new lesson today's a dharma day hence
the whiteboard
and dupaya days in which i review the
practices on the appiah days
we also alternate uh between practicing
the ecology practices from the eastern
tradition
and then practicing the the course on
wisdom
the wisdom of hypatia from the western
tradition if you're joining us for the
first time
don't be put off by this odd setup uh
please go to
uh the description you'll find links to
previous sits
where i'm sitting and uh there's an
uh and contemplation practices going on
there i recommend
that you go and do the first lesson
immediately
then try and do one or two lessons per
week keep meeting with us
and you will quickly integrate and catch
up
i would ask you all to please help me uh
to reach as many people as possible by
liking this use
youtube this youtube video stream
and raising its visibility in the
youtube algorithm um
at the end of the session today there
will be
uh well at the end of every session in
fact there is a q a please limit the
questions at that time
uh to anything from the entire ecology
of practices
we give priority on monday tuesday
monday wednesdays and fridays to
questions from the western tradition
because it's the one we're doing more
recently
and tuesdays and thursdays are from the
eastern tradition
if you have more general questions
please join us
on our live stream general q
a on youtube on every third friday of
the month
we just had one last friday was
excellent every 35 every third friday
the month
at 3 p.m eastern time um i think that's
everything right now
that we need in order to start i'll i
will make an effort to
write neater we're much more tightly
focused on the board
so hopefully for all of that we'll get
everything uh working well okay so we
were taking a look
at uh the epicurean
and we've up until now we've been
concentrating on one of the two polls of
epicureanism which is dealing with
our our desires dealing with pleasure
now we want to move from
the discussion of desire uh to the
discussion
of fear of course uh the two are related
because fear
is usually a sense that something that
we desire is under threat so they're not
completely separate
but we are moving to a different
emphasis now i
am very much in the same mind with
mclennan on this
he doesn't regard epicureanism as
sufficient
he regards it as a necessary and
powerful
first stage i like to think of
epicureanism as primary school
stoicism is high school and neoplatonism
as university
i think it's important to remember that
especially with the topics that we're
going to wrestle with today
um now while i find well i find
with mcclellan and others that the
epicurean
cures or solutions that we're going to
talk about today
are not sufficient i nevertheless
acknowledge
that many people throughout the ancient
world many people
found them sufficient and that means
that they are at least should be
recognized
as powerful and therefore worthy of
respect
and that they can at least be extremely
helpful
if not you know ultimate and
ultimate in their ability to afford us
to deal with some of the ultimate issues
we're going to talk about today
all right so the dealing with fear
um so there's a kind of fear that's
being talked about here it's important
um it's not so much instinctive fear
that we get as biological
entities uh the kind of fear that we
share with cats and dogs and things like
that
because of course being instinctive
there's not too much we can do about
that
uh what the epicureans though are
talking about is
um the way in which we self-terrify
ourselves uh because of our
undisciplined imaginations so
let me say that again we self-terrify
because of undisciplined
imagination
okay so let's take a quick look at this
we can help procure us out by following
his model of using the best science of
the time what is our best account
of what imagination is and here i'm
talking about
uh what's called the imaginary like
mental imagery
not what corbyn calls the imaginal or
we'll come back to the imaginal much
later
so the best idea uh and because i've
given you some
background on this i can make use of it
is
that imagination is basically the
predictive
prehension function
so if you remember when we talked about
savoring
there's perception which is the bottom
up opening up of new information from
the world
and the prehension is the act of looking
for patterns
finding patterns seeking patterns
and the idea of what's called predictive
processing is
that what your brain does is it tries to
predict the patterns
it's going to encounter before it
encounters them because that's way more
adaptive
and then what imagination is is when you
run this predictive
prediction apprehension of patterns
independent of getting new information
from the world that's why we often close
our eyes in order to imagine better
right so all you're getting is the
top-down
prediction of patterns that are going to
be grasped in the world
and you're actually cutting off all the
flow of incoming
information now the problem with that is
perception gives you the data that
corrects when these predictions are
wrong
so when we move to imagination we are
we're engaging something that's very
powerful very needed for us i'm not
i'm not a calvinist i don't hate the
imagination but we have to remember that
imagination on its own
is very very lopsided
it's because it is
prediction without data it is a place
that is very susceptible to cognitive
bias
because without that incoming data our
theorizing if you'll allow me to use
that as a metaphor is unconstrained
and our worst biases come to the fore
and so an undisciplined imagination is
an imagination
that is especially rife with cognitive
biasing
and the problem in our culture is we've
had two traditions around the
imagination
one i've just mentioned calvin it's a
puritanical thing that says
you know the imagination is a permanent
factory for the production of idols the
imaginati
you know idol hands or the devil's
workshop and and then we've had the
romantics who said that imagination is
is the root to god etc and both of these
as they were at war with themselves in
their extremism
both of them ignore the proper
education of the imagination
and not just repressing it like the
calvinist and not just
expressing it like the romantics
so we need i one way of understanding
the epicureans is that they had a method
for trying
to educate the imagination
because unconstrained the imagination
is a place that is
beset with cognitive bias but properly
educated and think about this this is
the befriending there's no enemy worse
than your own mind and body
but there's no friend that's greater but
an educated imagination is one of our
most powerful allies
okay so let's think of it that way so
there
they have what they call the four-fold
cure
for fear where fear again isn't that
instinctive taking your hand away from
the fire
but the way in which we sort of terrify
ourselves
with our imagination so the four full
cure is a set of maxims
and so you're supposed to use it in
maximization and what
we're going to learn today is the
practice of
reflective explication okay
so a maxim has a lot of ideas compressed
so it's easy to transport around and
remember but you have to remember that a
maxim is just a remember
doorway and the point of a maxim is
always to make explicit that's what
explicate means explicate is not
a synonym for imagine explicate means to
make
explicit what is implicit okay we want
to explicate
the maximum and we want to do this
reflectively
okay so reflective explication
okay so let's take a look at these
maxims and go through them and explicate
them
we're going to explicate them
reflectively what are we reflecting on
we're reflecting on
how we can educate our moments of
imagination
so what i'm teaching here is something
that you bring
into practice when you start to imagine
when you start to imagine
okay so the first of the fourfold cures
is a very famous one and
we've got to do some work on it because
its relevancy has changed i think
because we're not in the same situation
the gods or god
are not to be feared
okay so let's put this into the first
the historical situation
there's a multiplicity of gods in the
ancient world they're very capricious
um they don't act according to moral
principles and then what epicurus
basically argues
is those kinds of gods don't exist the
only kinds of gods that could exist are
ones that are sages
that have wisdom and therefore they
would have no reason to be capricious or
act immorally towards us etc
and that sort of aspect of it has
largely been taken care of
uh by a couple of millennia of
christianity in which we have been
taught
that god is good or or and and you know
and i'm not advocating for the existence
of god uh
i mean i'm gonna put that problem aside
i'm gonna talk about it in the series of
the god beyond god
what i think we can draw from this
are two different fears that were
present
behind this mythological representation
in the ancient world
that are still relevant to us today that
the first
is the fear of fate where fate
doesn't necessarily mean destiny fate
means
um the the how things are beyond
our control beyond our understanding
and uh a book i recommend about how this
was the one of the central issues
in the ancient world is a book called
beyond fate
uh by margaret visser beyond fate and
notice the title beyond fate
what what was going on in the ancient
world was a way of
trying to find a way of living that was
beyond fate um
notice that we get this word out of it
fatality fatality doesn't or didn't
originally mean having to do with death
fatality meant when something struck us
that was beyond our control beyond our
understanding beyond the narrative
structure of our lives right death of
course is a primary example
of being struck by something beyond our
control and outside the narrative
control of our life
but many things many things
relationships career
many things are subject to fatality in
that sense
so please remember that please remember
that we're going to need to know that
especially when we talk about stoicism
okay so what this turns what
what you can see in here is this is a
fear of two facts about us our finitude
that we are finite and our fallibility
that we will always be making mistakes
okay and the
the basic answer and that comes from
visser's
title that the ancient world came up
with beyond fate
was a recognition that although human
beings are subject
to finitude infallibility they are also
capable
of transcendence they are capable of
transcendence and virtue so virtuous
transcendence
right was the main idea
and you may say well that doesn't
protect me it doesn't protect you
from the events and here's where
stoicism is going to be much more
helpful than epicureanism
but it protects you to a large degree
from a meaning from the meaning of the
events
remember we're not talking about you
know events that we have an instinctive
reaction to
we're talking about the meaning of
events when
we imagine about them or project
our projects or concerns onto them
so the idea uh that we are capable of
finite transcendence however
isn't really that well discussed
in epicureanism so here's one area where
i think it's inadequate
i think epicureanism provides us a place
where we can start to experience it
like in adoraxia but it wasn't very well
discussed
when we get to neoplatonism stoicism and
then neoplatonism we'll see that there
is a very good way of
addressing finite transcendence but for
those of you who have been through the
course already
you already have a lot of that empowered
in you
from the eastern tradition because
that's exactly what meditation and
contemplation bring about they have you
accept your finitude
while affording your capacity for
virtuous transcendence
neoplatonism says that what we are
actually looking for
as a response to fate is to come into
contact
with what is most real what is most real
and that's of course what transcendence
is it's a longing to come into right
relationship
with what is ultimately real and so
degree to which we can cultivate a right
relationship with what is ultimately
real
we can address this side so
there's a little bit here in
epicureanism but i think this is where
we will need
uh neoplatonism to re stoicism and
neoplate and neoplatonism to really give
us a more comprehensive answer
now here is one where the epicureans did
do a lot
and this is um about
the afterlife um
and so this is a very of course fraught
issue uh for a lot of people and i'll
try and speak on the epicureans behalf
but
um my own view i can't keep my own view
completely separate from this
but i'm trying its best to mediate
epicurus
to you a reminder by the way that uh
monday wednesdays and fridays are longer
classes
we're not going to get through all of
this lesson today we're going to have
this week is going to be a three dharma
day monday
wednesday and friday will all be dormant
days
okay so the afterlife
okay so we can make use of epicurus here
um and
scientifically improbable okay
so the idea that something of me
can survive the the undeniable death of
my brain and body
um is coming increasingly um improbable
as our knowledge of the brain and
the mind's relationship to the brain
grows
um it's coming to the and so and this is
something taken very seriously by
foreign cognitive science we are deeply
embodied
um the idea that our cognition could in
any way
exist or function separately from our
embodied brain
is becoming really
deeply deeply questionable um
so there's that but you say well it's
not based on science
and that's right and i got acknowledged
and then
that's where we have to acknowledge that
we're using imagination
we're thinking mythically which doesn't
mean we're necessarily thinking falsely
i'm not simplistic like that
but then the epicureans right did a lot
to try and
sort of critique the mythology
of the afterlife in their world what can
we do about ours well
for me this is what i do you may find it
helpful and here's again where i go
outside epicurus the eastern traditions
have a very different view of
immortality
than the west life after death it is
viewed with horror
personal immortality is not thought to
be a good thing
it is thought to be a fundamentally
horrific thing
because we are we are we are finite and
we're fallible
and extending that uh forever and ever
would be uh horrible but this is why the
let's think of a vedanta the the thing
you seek is moksa
muksha you seek release from
reincarnation
you seek release from immortality or
nirvana to blow out you seek release
from personal immortality because if you
think about it
what what do you what would you want
well i want to just keep doing all the
things that i do
but forever and
would you want to do them would you want
to watch your friends die well i need my
friends to all keep
living forever and then you're going to
be living with them forever can you even
live with anybody
more one or two people for a lifetime
think about how hard it is to be
married and then but my friends are
going to need their friends and family
and their friends and family and their
friends and family and then the work
so what you want is the world to freeze
but with that forever would that be a
good thing
do you really want that see this is what
i mean you have to
if you're going to imagine imagine in a
disciplined
rational fuller manner
open up really follow out the
implications of your imagery
don't get fixated on the image expand it
out and that's what the epicureans
keep getting us to do now i'm drawing
from the eastern tradition but the
practice of disciplining the imagination
and really expanding it out is very very
helpful
it comes from epicurus so
[Music]
now what you may say here is okay
what's really going on here right so no
i don't know
not only is it
scientifically impo probable
you want to you want to transform the
myth
i'm just writing this poorly
open it up to many alternative
mythologies
in which immortality is imagined
in a fuller richer way and revealed to
be something
potentially quite horrific
okay so you say that's all fine and good
and that's not what was really going on
what's really going on in immortality
is the fear of death
so what we're really trying to do is
avoid our mortality
um that's what's and now this is where
the epicureans are terrifically helpful
once again we must make a distinction
between that you know
a version of the distinction i've
already made we must distinguish between
our fear of death as an instinctive
thing
like avoiding the fire which we share
with all animals and our fear of our
mortality
animals are not aware of their mortality
they fear
they instinctively avoid threats to
their biological life
but they do not have the capacity to
fall into despair
about their mortality and that's what
we're talking about here
the despair about your mortality
so there's two things that need to be
separated here
which the epicureans do one is the fear
of non-existence
and the other is the fear of dying
okay so the epicureans say the fear of
non-existence
and then what they're going to try and
do is they're going to try and say
you're actually
imagining in a self-contradictory manner
first of all they say
you don't fear non-existence the thought
of non-existence isn't itself terrifying
and what they do is they say
what i want you to do is imagine all of
the time before you existed
you weren't there just imagine it
terrifying to you
most people say no i just i wasn't there
it doesn't matter
right so
you say but it's the fear of me being
non-existent not just that well you were
non-existent before you were born
so there's something else mixed up there
right there's something else confused in
the image
they bring in another one they say well
your non-existence
is not something you can ever experience
epicurus famously said
where death is i am not where i am death
is not
namely if i'm in non-existence i can
never know it
it is not something i can ever
experience
so i should never be afraid of it and as
long as i'm experiencing
that means i still exist and therefore i
shouldn't be afraid of non-existence
now you might feel like that's just sort
of a logical trick but what it's
getting you to do is to say what is it
you're
actually imagining
that's at the core of your fear of
non-existence
now i think what's happening here
is that our death is something that is
mysterious to us
and i mean precisely that not not in
that
just something we don't know a mystery
is
and that's the basis of the word
mystical is something that we cannot
directly comprehend now we have to be
careful
i can comprehend my non-existence
propositionally i can say
i didn't exist in the year 1888 i won't
exist in the year 4054.
that's no problem but what i can't do
is experientially
i can't experience even in my
imagination
my own non-existence because whenever i
try to imagine it
i'm actually there experience it and
therefore i fall into self-contradiction
and so there's something ungraspable
not conceptually but experientially
about my
my own so literally that's what i'm
proposing to you
non-existence is something that's
unimaginable
and what's actually happening i suggest
you this is what the epicureans are
saying
is your imagination machinery is
panicking
because it can't predict this because
it's not imaginable
it's not imaginable and so it turns it
into an um
it turns it into some unpredictable
thing
when in fact that's a mistake
how could we respond to the that
experience because
your imagination confronting something
that is a mystery to it
something that is actually a black hole
in your imagination
oh and this is again where i think
neoplatonism
is going to come into play
we need more practice in the positive
experience
of mystery of that which exceeds our
imagination which has a no thing-ness to
us
so the cultivation of awe
gives us a education of
right that reduces the panic that our
imagination
comes into when it confronts something
that is mysterious to us
okay what also happens
and that's very helpful here
is again to remember that continued
un you know forever immortal existence
is also horrific and that is something
you can
imagine to some degree but when you
start to extend it towards infinity
and your imagination starts to block
everything of value
because given an infinite amount of time
you are going to be
go through so many changes that you will
be completely different
from the person you are all the
relationships you have could they
survive
all of the time all of infinity
we are mortal and our meaning is the
meaning of mortals
and uh the line from melville comes to
me right here from moby dick
what is man that he should try to seek
out to live out the lifetime of his god
right okay so we're about halfway
through the four-fold cure
it sounds like what you've got sort of
one and a half
on wednesday we're going to talk about
the fear of dying
which is not the same thing as the fear
of non-existence
the fear of dying is something you can
experience you can go through the
process
of loss what i'm going to show you is
this is precisely the place
where our imagination runs wild
and we can address the fear of dying by
getting
bringing a better by bringing some of
the best cognitive science we have to
bear on
educating our imagination around
the future of us dying
okay and then we will continue on with
and that will lead us into the two other
aspects of the four-fold cure
right your fear of loss of pleasure your
fear of increase in pain
and that will actually come out of the
fear of dying
and so we're halfway through but what
what you can do right now
is you can start to catalog the kinds of
imaginings you have
when and the imaginings that are
bringing about self terrifying
when there's imaginings about fate
think about the capacity for
transcendence
and coming into right relationship with
what is most real
because that seems to allay that fear
for the fear of the afterlife
think about its scientific improbability
and think about
well nevertheless you may have a mythic
and i remember for me that's not an
insult word
they have a mythic imagination of it but
then remember
that maybe you should extend and more
fully develop
with the help of the eastern traditions
what that mythic imagination
is really like and do you really want
that more developed
imagined afterlife then
that will actually take you to okay
what's actually at work here
is not the quest for immortality it's
the fear of mortality
and i'm sorry i'm going to leave you
sort of halfway through and i apologize
for that
i can't teach everything at once and i'm
finite infallible
and we have limited time
but you have to break up your fear of
death into two things the fear of
non-existence which is
actually absurd it's not something
it's not what what's actually happening
is is not anything you imagine
it's your imagination is encountering
something that is mysterious
to it something that is ungraspable
unpredictable and that is panicking
our brain does not like what it cannot
predict
but it's not unpredictable because it's
an uncertain event in the future
that's a mistake it's unpredictable
because our imaginative faculty can't
grasp it
then what do you then what's the
response then you say to yourself
i need to get better at confronting
mystery i need to and we have an
emotional experience
ah that allows us to encounter mystery
in a much more positive and
transformative
manner and you've already been
practicing some of that in the eastern
practices
so as i said i'm sorry um to leave it's
about halfway through the four-fold cure
i'll quickly review this on wednesday
what we've done so far i'll finish it up
and did you notice i'm indicating
throughout that i don't think the
epicureans are sufficient
we need more i try to indicate where
that's going to come in but i want to
finish the epicureans
on the fourfold cure on wednesday and
then i want to get to where do we
actually go to get the courage to be
where do we go to practice this kind of
reflection
and that's in philosophical
contemplative
companionships in philosophical
friendship which is at the core
of the epicurean practices where we
learn to savor
we learned to savor each other i i i
wanted to say that and then i
i stopped because it sounded so trite it
sounds like a
hallmark card but savoring each other in
a way that brings about profound
anoraxia and joy as something distinct
from happiness
the kind of happiness we pursue in our
culture so we're going to talk about
that on friday
and how to practice it so again
wednesday and friday also going to be
long classes
so i'm going to sit now we're going to
do a very uh
very brief meditative set we won't be
able to take uh
i think any questions today uh we will
try and take
extra questions tomorrow and on
wednesday thursday friday
again i ask for your patience uh
teaching you the wisdom of hypatia is
is not as compressible as teaching you
uh what i taught you uh uh from the
buddhist and davos tradition so i'm
gonna sit down now
here jason's gonna adjust the camera
we'll have a quick
sit
together and then we will end for today
so please get yourself comfortable set
your phones on do not disturb i'm sort
of looking up to you
that's good there are rituals uh where
the teacher
is supposed to periodically sit below
the feet of the students
because it reminds him or her of
um the true nature of their existence
so this is helpful uh okay so
we'll have a short chant and then we'll
go into a short silent sit
and then we'll come out of it together
and like i said unfortunately uh we
won't be able to take a lot of questions
today
your questions will not be lost i
promise they will be addressed
throughout the week okay
so set your phones and do not disturb we
will begin when i say begin
begin
one
getting your silence set
you
[Music]
slowly come out of your practice trying
his best what you cultivated in your
practice
to integrate it with your everyday
consciousness and cognition
character and communitas perhaps by
reciting the five promises to yourself
so as i said we've already run quite
long but i have forewarned you that
monday wednesdays and fridays when it's
dharma
will tend to be longer as we pursue the
wisdom of hypatia
thank you all for joining i want to
remind everyone if they can
to join subscribe to this video channel
you'll find links to lecture series
awakening from the meeting crisis to the
dialogue of series voices with verveiki
you'll be notified of updates if it's
not against your principles i ask you to
please consider
following me on twitter so you can know
about talks and events
and changes to any of these streams that
might
come out come about last minute please
join the discord server
you'll find people practicing the
movement practices doing ever extra
meditation discussing all this series
and uh having people in there that are
from the voices with verveiki
uh the logo series um there
is going to be a home there for the
group practices that we're going to
start engaging in we're going to start
learning about
this week so i please ask you to
join the discord server so that you'll
find it
a welcoming home for the group practices
that are so central
to the wisdom of hypatia
so remember that continuity practice is
more important than sure quantity of
practice
don't hold yourself to a harsh standard
of perfectionism
but to a standard that recognizes your
mortality
a standard of virtuous friendship
friendship the kind of friendship that's
at the heart of epicureanism
remembering especially with respect to
the imagination that we talked about
today
there's no enemy worse than your own
mind and body but there's no friend no
ally no true companion on the path
greater than your own mind and body
relapse into yourselves and to each
other
take good care everyone we'll get to
some of your questions tomorrow i
promise